5 Lussac Court Lake St. Louis, MO 63367

# WILLIAM M. MAINTZ II

bill@allbusinesscomputerservices.com

H: (636) 625-1118 C: (314) 852-6074

# **CAREER SUMMARY**

Senior-level Project Manager with progressively responsible experience in Information Technology Management, Operational Analysis and Control, and Management Information Systems. Possesses a well-rounded management background in the conception, design, development, and implementation of a full array of computer software products and systems. A versatile communicator who has demonstrated excellent oral and written communication skills by delivering technical and business information to diverse audiences, from small senior management groups to large convention assemblies. Recognized for his ability to bridge the technical and business aspects of the organization as the technology changes and impacts core business values.

### **KEY COMPETENCIES**

Information Technology Management
<b>Business Process Improvement</b>
Systems and Procedures Development
SDLC Environment Management
Technical Leadership/Mentoring

Project Management Operational Analysis Planning/Organizing Change Management Data Modeling/Design Health Plan Payor Operations Software Development Management Personnel and Staff Development System Architecture Design Testing/Quality Assurance/Control

#### **SELECTED ACHIEVEMENTS**

# Refined business process flow for faster and less costly claims adjudication

As the Senior Project Manager for Noridian Healthcare Solutions (NHS), I was responsible for managing the implementation of a new claims processing subsystem that would increase speed, reduce the per transaction cost, and increase NHS's ability and flexibility to quickly address new client needs. NHS processed claims for CMS Jurisdictions E & F, Medicaid claims for Iowa Medicaid, and commercial claims for BCBSND and BCBSWY. Even though a common claims processing engine was used for all lines of business, separate process flows were defined to address the specific needs of each line of business and the commercial claims process flow required the added approval of the BCBS Association. The solution required the coordinated efforts of two third party software vendors, multiple hardware vendors, and the matrixed management of team members from multiple internal departments of Noridian.

#### Controlled the cost of delivery through environment management

On the Blue Shield of California Facets software implementation project, involving multiple teams, multiple tracks of development, and the integration of multiple sub-systems connecting to the main software application, I helped control the costs associated with implementing such a complex project and of this magnitude by controlling the number of environments created for development, testing, training, and staging and by coordinating the scheduled use of those environments. As the Environment Governance Manager, I met with up to 40 company departmental representatives, of the multiple teams and development tracts, to determine when an additional environment was needed/justified and what additional hardware and/or subsystems would be included in that environment when completed.

#### Developed a requirements gathering and cost-justification process

Qualitech Computer Centers needed a process that their business representatives could use to gather the business requirements of their potential clients and help them determine the size and complexity of each client's new computer system. I created a 37 page questionnaire and complimentary needs-analysis computer program that would allow their reps to gather the clients' business requirements and, upon entering their responses to the questions into the computer program, would use that information to determine the size of the computer system and the specific computer hardware and software needed to fulfill those requirements. The program would further calculate the cost of the complete system, calculate the cost savings that could be realized once the system was implemented, and generate a 26 page "Management Blueprint" Business Proposal and Cost Justification document used to present the solution to the client. This process was so successful in the field, that it became a valued and effective component of Qualitech's marketing strategy system.

# WILLIAM M. MAINTZ II

5 Lussac Court Lake St. Louis, MO 63367 H: (636) 625-1118 C: (314) 852-6074

#### **EDUCATION**

Southern Illinois University

Edwardsville, IL

1988

B.S. in Business Administration/Management Information Systems with a minor in Mathematics

#### **LANGUAGES AND TECHNOLOGIES**

- Windows NT / 95 / 98 / 2000 / 2003 / 2008 / 2012 / XP / Vista / 7 / 8 / 10, Azure, UNIX, AIX, HP/UX, LINUX
- C, C++, C#, Visual Basic, VBA, VB Script, Java, JavaScript, JSP, JSON, JQuery, Windows Script, PowerShell, UNIX Shell Script (sh, ksh, csh), PERL, HTML/HTML5, Razor CSHTML, CSS/CSS3, ASP.NET, ADO.NET, MVC, XSLT, XML, XAML, Silverlight (3-5), Entity Framework, AngularJS, KnockoutJS, Bootstrap.js, node.js
- Sybase (11.x, 12.x, 15.x), Oracle (7.x, 8i, 9, 11), MS SQL Server (6.5, 7.0, 2005, 2008, 2010, 2012, 2016), Informix, DB2/2, ERwin DB Modeling (3.5.2), Power Designer 10.0
- WebSphere, PDC, DNS, DHCP, IIS, ISA Server, Web Services, Terminal Server
- MS Office (2003-2013) (Word, Excel, Access, PowerPoint, OneNote, Outlook, Publisher), SharePoint, MS
  Project, MS Visio, TFS, Visual Studio (6-2013), VS Code, Expression Blend (3-4), InfoPath, TFS, SourceSafe,
  PVCS, sccs, git, Jira, Apache Ant, npm, grunt, bower, yeoman, Karma, Protractor, Subversion, Eclipse, MS IE,
  Netscape, Google Chrome, Firefox, EC Gateway, SSIS, SSMS, SSRS, Crystal Reports, Business Objects, Data
  Integrator, Brio, HPXR, Clarity
- EDI, X12, ETL, Data Mart, Data Warehouse, n-tier App Dev, TriZetto/Erisco FACETS versions 2.94-5.01, Broadband RF, Bar Code Labeling

#### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

### Owner/Manager

### All Business Computer Services LLC

2005 - Present

#### Worked on numerous projects for various clients, performing the following functions:

- Provided business and technical project management and leadership throughout the full SDLC model.
- Helped conceive, define, and design complete system and subsystem architectures
- Facilitated requirements gathering sessions (business and technical) and documented the outcome.
- Defined, designed, documented, and illustrated detailed and complex business process flows
- Defined data models and data flows for primary applications, data marts, and data warehouses.
- Managed and was a part of application development processes throughout the full SDLC model.
- Defined QA procedures and testing activities to better identify defects.
- Facilitated meetings for small groups (up to 40 participants) and larger audiences like large convention assemblies.

# ABCS Client/Project List (Client [- Project] - Position Held)

- True Manufacturing Kentico CMS Web Page Projects (QR Code and SVG File Parts Search) Developer
- Fidelis Care Sybase Database Version Upgrade Developer
- Lumeris/Essence Healthcare EHR Transaction Processing Senior Application Developer
- GEHA Facets Implementation & Data Warehouse Business Analyst and Report Designer
- MED3OOO Facets Upgrade Technical Lead, Web Portal Development
- HealthNow of New York Facets Upgrade Project/Environment Manager
- Western & Southern Financial Life Facets Implementation Technical Analyst
- Blue Shield of California Facets Implementation Architect, SCRM PM, Environment Governance Lead, & Infrastructure Architect.
- APS Healthcare Facets Upgrade Technical Lead, QA Manager, & Project Co-Manager
- Blue Cross Blue Shield of Louisiana Facets Implementation Project Manager / Technical Lead
- OSF Healthcare Facets Upgrade & Data Warehouse Technical Lead

# Senior Project Manager

#### Beacon Hill Technologies

2014

Sr. Project Mgr. on Multiple Projects

**Express Scripts** 

2014 testing,

- Three Major Projects Lead multiple teams of onshore and offshore personnel in the design, development, testing, and deployment of multiple components that were all a part of single and multi-release projects (separate release(s) over a six month span).
- All three projects were brought in under-budget, saving the company almost one million dollars in the process. Project 1-budgeted at \$2.75m and delivered for \$2.2m. Project 2-budgeted at \$675K and delivered for under \$400K. Project 3-budgeted at \$527K and delivered for \$400K.

# WILLIAM M. MAINTZ II

5 Lussac Court Lake St. Louis, MO 63367

Senior Consultant GenPact/Jawood Healthcare Solutions

2013-2014

H: (636) 625-1118

C: (314) 852-6074

ICD-10 Assessment Lead Horizon Blue Cross Blue Shield

2014

# ICD-10 Business Operational Testing Readiness Assessment Project

- Lead ICD-10 Business Operational Testing Readiness Assessment Team to help client determine whether or not Horizon BCBS was ready for the ICD-10 implementation on October 1, 2014.
- Separated master ICD-10 questionnaire (450 questions) into 34 unique department/area questionnaires used as the basis for each facilitated question and answer session.
- Facilitated question and answer sessions between client and consulting agency subject matter experts.

**EPMO Senior Project Manager** 

Noridian Healthcare Solutions

2013

# **TIBCO EDI Front-End Replacement Project**

- Responsible for the full SDLC model definition, development, testing, and promotion of a highly scalable claims
  processing and adjudication system.
- Provided executives with weekly status reports detailing the progress, issues, and risks. The dashboard and format of those status reports became a template to use for all project managers within the EPMO.
- Coordinated the replacement of their EDI Front-End system with the TIBCO suite of applications.
- Helped define and design the architecture of the infrastructure.
- Helped define the development and testing environments both systems and activities within each.
- Helped assess the needed employee training and coordinated/scheduled its delivery.
- Integrated the 3<sup>rd</sup> party software vendor's project plan with the NHS project plan (Waterfall methodology).
- Provided business and technical leadership in defining the process flows
- Incorporated the diverse needs of 5010 EDI processing, the ICD-10 codes implementation, the Affordable Care Act (PPACA or Obama Care), the Health Insurance Exchange (HIX), Medicare, Medicaid, and the BCBS Association.

### **Provider Portal Project**

• Utilized the Agile development methodology and Jira to manage, track, and report the project's progress.

# Senior Consultant La

Lanier & Associates, Atlanta, GA

2003 - 2005

- TriZetto Hosting Center Technical Lead
  - Blue Cross Blue Shield of Michigan Facets Implementation Technical Lead
  - United Healthcare Database Merge Technical Lead
  - Caresource Indiana Data Conversion Technical Lead

Senior Consultant

Partec, Inc., St. Louis, MO

2000 - 2002

- Blue Cross Blue Shield of Missouri Project Manager & Technical Lead (multiple projects)
- CoForce.com CIO
- Computer Sales International Project Co-Manager, Application Designer, & Application Developer

President

## All Business Computer Services Inc.

1991 - 2000

Working as a computer consultant for multiple clients, developed a Customer Support Website for WAN Technologies, developed a network communications subsystem for Bridge Communications, created a Single Sign-On front-end for Illinois Masonic Medical Center, designed and administered the Application Data Model for Omnus in their application, OmniPlan, lead a technical team in implementing a multi-server Distributed Warehouse Management System that interfaced with the production line and lead the development of a Data Warehouse for Ralston Purina.

## **Independent Consultant**

# Anderson Consulting.

1989 - 1991

 Working as a computer consultant for multiple clients, designed and created an online help subsystem for Ralston Purina, lead a development team in producing an Image Storage & Retrieval System using APPC Communication for Citicorp Mortgage, and lead a development team in creating an Executive Presentation System for May Company.

#### Divisional Vice President Plus Five Computer Software, St. Louis, MO

1988 - 1989

• Managed the development of a new product, "Voxel 4-D", a real-time 3D image rendering system for the display of medical CAT-Scan and MRI data on 50 different UNIX platforms.